Guide to the University of Pittsburgh History and Memorabilia Collection, 1894-1989 UA.0.3A
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh History and Memorabilia Collection
1894-1989
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Starrett, Agnes Lynch
UA.0.3A
0.4 Linear Feet (1 box)
This is a collection of brochures, articles, reports and other materials about the history of the University.
Scope and Content Notes
This is a collection of articles, reports, brochures and miscellaneous informational documents that generally trace the history of the University of Pittsburgh. It is divided into chronological periods.
See Also
Other collection in UA Record Group 0 also has general historical files.
Previous Citation
University of Pittsburgh History and Memorabilia Collection, 1894-1989, UA.0.3A, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was likely kept by Agnes Lynch Starrett.
Related Material
Agnes Lynch Starrett Research Files on the History of the University of Pittsburgh, UA.0.3.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; University of Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh -- History; University of Pittsburgh -- Collectibles
- Pittsburgh Academy and Western University of Pennsylvania, 1894-1908 (Box 1, Folder 1-1a)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Pittsburgh Academy and Western University of Pennsylvania 1787-1907 list of Chancellors (title first given to Woods, 1858;) Description of Western University of Pennsylvania in School Herald, 1895; facsimile of Recommendation letter signed by Principal McLaren, 1858; sketch of early Pittsburgh life; description of WUP in American University magazine, 1897; Plan of WUP in Oakland, 1908; brochure, "A college education in Pittsburgh, 1905; article on Catholic priest who served on original faculty; petition to Pennsylvania Assembly to use Western Penitentiary for the University, 1883; Photocopy of indexed Teachers' Club Scrapbook containing newspaper/periodical articles relating to WUP 1879 (1 article 1868); Legislative Acts re: establishing Academy in FF 1A.
- Western University of Pennsylvania and the University of Pittsburgh, 1909-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Article on 127th year celebration, 1914; humorous rules for freshmen, 1909; list of university faculty, 1915; information books sent to prospective students, 1914-1920; address by ex-Chancellor Holland, 1912; various brochures, e.g. service of University to the state, 1917; Map of Oakland site.
- History, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Photocopies of articles in Pittsburgh Gazette Times, January 4, 11, 18, 1920 and May 10, 1925 by George Fleming; early Pittsburgh history and Pitt; article "Sidelights on University history" 1926; "Pitt, the adolescent year, 1908-28" by George Ketchum, 1971; Legislative askings, 1923-25; misc. brochures from 1920's; Map 1928.
- History and the building of the Cathedral of Learning, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  University history, largely about building the Cathedral, written 1934 (Of note is paragraph about government funds to finish building during the depression on p.5); brochures for prospective students; clipping about W & J or Pitt being older; brief submitted to Pennsylvania House of Representatives in 1935 re firing of Professor Turner; article "from Log Cabin to Cathedral, 1932.
- History, 1940-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Clippings about Pitt reinstated to the AAUP after 11 years; brochures about University life; 1948 faculty panel "What kind of university by 1960?" Brochures and clippings on proposed campus expansion, building on Cathedral lawn and new health center. (see also Memorabilia of World War II activities for more material on this time period); List of accomplishments of 12 chancellors, 1819-1955.
- History, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Post Gazette – Pitt 175 years, 1962; "A Light in the City" booklet on Pitt's progress; visitors guides and informational brochures; 1965 "Fact Book" guide to undergraduate education; article in French by visiting scholar attending Management problems for executives course; "Aims and Purposes (of University) statement, undated; News release on Ford Foundation study, 1965; various clippings on Litchfield years; Report to the community, 1955-65; news release "University committee to study faculty flight from teaching. "Those wonderful years" pamphlet; "A Light in the City" 1964; "Toward Five Goals" 1963 Report; "This is the University of Pittsburgh" 1964
- History and State-Related Status, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Copy of Pennsylvania General Assembly House Bill No. 2, making Pitt state related, 1966; Barrons profile in depth study of American Colleges – University of Pittsburgh, 1968 and 1973; small Pitt Profile brochures and quick facts; "Impact of the University on the local economy," 1972 and 1975-76; "University and the regional economy," 1975/76; "Pitt at a Glance" 1977; articles: Higher education in Pennsylvania; on university governance; 3 roles of the Chancellor; Pittsburgh Press series on higher education in Pittsburgh, 1976; ROTC and Black studies, 1969; articles responding to campus unrest, 1969; pictures of campus departments on Craig street, 1970; articles on the external degree, 1972; P-G editorial – Pitt joins AAU, 1974
- History, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Highlights and History brochures with campus map, 1979-1985; Article by Moll: "Public Ivys"; brochures, 1979, 1983; Admissions booklet, 1979.
- Postcards, 1937-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- History (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Memorabilia from William S. McIntyre through D. Arthur George (Dentistry) on the University flag pole 1915-16 University checks 1931-32; stadium 1924
- Pittsburgh Academy Historical Marker (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Proof of Location by Iva Richey Parkas.